This episode of Primal Space is supported by Skillshare.
哪个男孩不想乘坐猎鹰九号火箭以超过每小时500公里的速度下降？
You are currently riding onboard a Falcon 9 rocket as it descends through the atmosphere at over 500km/h.
而你的坐骑将会有如下逆天操作：
What happens next is truly incredible.
在最后的千钧一发之际 火箭的发动机会点火 然后稳稳落在一艘无人船上
At the last possible second, it fires up its engines and lands perfectly in the middle of the droneship.
但这早已是基本操作 火箭回收这种东西太空叉早就玩好多年了
But there's nothing new about this, SpaceX have been landing rockets for years.
牛逼的是我们竟然能看到实时的直播！
But what is impressive is that we actually saw it live!
从太空叉开始回收火箭的时候 他们就一直纠结怎么直播这样的画面
Ever since they started landing rockets, SpaceX have had a problem actually showing us.
回收通常是每次发射任务中最令人激动的环节
It's arguably the most exciting part of each mission,
但着陆区的相机总是会在火箭马上要落下来的时候断流
but the cameras at the landing zone are well known for cutting out, just as the rocket comes into frame.
当然了 有人会说这是太空叉买不起显卡跑不动这么逼真的特效
Of course, some people will claim that this is where SpaceX ran out of their special effects budget.
但事实上 这背后的原因非常复杂
But actually, the problem is much more complex.
大家要知道 每次在船上的着陆通常在离岸几百公里的大洋上
You have to remember that each droneship landing usually takes place hundreds of kilometers off-shore.
当火箭起飞后飞向大西洋后
When the rocket starts to head out over the Atlantic,
它会向在佛罗里达的地面站发送视频信号
it sends telemetry and a video signal down to a ground station in Florida.
随着火箭越飞越远
As the rocket gets further away from Florida,
会在某一刻中断与地面站的联系 切换到与回收船通讯
there is a point where it loses contact with the ground station and switches over to the droneship.
此时 火箭所有的通讯都是经由回收船进行的
From this point onwards, the rocket's only communication is with the droneship.
视频信号和其他重要的遥测数据会一起从火箭一级发出
The video signal (along with other important telemetry) is sent from the booster
用S波段无线电发机发送给无人船
to the droneship using an S-band transmitter.
这些无线电发机可以做得很小 而且受到云层和天气的影响很小
These transmitters can be really small and they are less affected by clouds and weather,
这让它们很适合用在卫星通信、气象雷达和机载WiFi上
making them perfect for things like communications satellites, weather radars and airplane WiFi.
猎鹰九号的两级火箭每个都有两台无线电发机
Both stages of the Falcon 9 are equipped with two S-band transmitters,
各自传送遥测数据和视频信号
which send the telemetry and video individually.
一级火箭与无人船的通讯是每次着陆中的重要一环
An important part of every landing is the booster's ability to communicate with the droneship.
无人船不会回复火箭的通讯 但会持续接受来自火箭的速度与位置数据
The droneship doesn't communicate back with the rocket, but it constantly receives speed and position data.
并让自己尽量保持在一个不变的位置上
The droneship does its best to stay in the exact same position,
为一级火箭提供一个稳定的靶心去瞄准
providing the booster with a stationary target to hit.
但通讯问题在火箭接近无人船之前就已经出现了
But the communication problems start before the rocket gets anywhere near the droneship.
随着火箭以高超音速再入大气
As the rocket reenters the atmosphere, it's travelling at hypersonic speeds.
箭体本身会与空气剧烈摩擦 产生大量热量 并让分子发生电离
The rocket heats up the air around it which breaks down the molecules,
在火箭底部一圈形成一层等离子体
causing a layer of plasma to form around the base of the rocket.
等离子体(在地球电离层)的频率是2-20MHz
Plasma has a natural frequency between 2 and 20 MHz.
当电磁波在靠近这个频率的等离子体时
As radio waves get closer to this frequency,
会被其吸收 使得自身很难穿透那一层等离子体
they get absorbed and have a harder time traveling through the plasma.
这会在信号中引入大量的噪声
This creates an enormous amount of noise in the signal
让无人船在火箭再入时无法正常接收火箭信号
and blocks it from reaching the droneship in its entirety.
但在最近的一些任务中 视频信号在降落的这个阶段中正常传回了
But in recent missions, the video signal has survived this portion of the landing,
让我们看到了非常壮观的火箭再入画面
giving us a great view of the rocket's reentry.
太空叉可能是在测试让无线电发机放在火箭的不同位置
SpaceX could be experimenting with their transmitters by placing them in different places on the rocket.
因为火箭再入的时候是有一定角度的
Since the rocket re-enters at an angle,
所以很可能有个小缺口能让无线电发机刚好从周围的等离子体中突围
it's likely that there is a thin window of space where the transmitters can avoid most of the plasma.
放到以前 火箭再入的时候视频信号基本都会断流
In the past, it was almost guaranteed that the video feed would cut out during the rocket's reentry.
但让火箭的信号发送到船上只解决了一半的问题
But getting the video signal from the rocket to the droneship is only half of the problem.
当无人船接收到了火箭的信号
If and when the video reaches the droneship,
还要把它转发给位于加州霍索恩的转播团队
it has to be sent back to the broadcast team in Hawthorne California.
而无人船在离岸上百英里的茫茫大洋上 那这一切就只能靠卫星了
Since the droneship is hundreds of miles out at sea, this can only be done via a satellite.
再过去 无人船使用的是定向天线 给信号上传给卫星
In the past, the droneship used a directional antenna to send the signal up to a satellite.
虽然这样信号更强
Although this offered a stronger signal,
但对天线指向精度有很高的要求 否则传输就会断流
it had to be incredibly accurate or else the signal wouldn't be transmitted.
于是第二个问题来了
This is where the second problem comes in.
当火箭马上就要着陆的时候 底部一台或者三台梅林发动机会点火
As the rocket comes in for a landing, it's slowed down using either 1 or 3 of it's Merlin engines,
梅林1D发动机海平面满推力为854kN 19.20万磅
节流后推力最小是482kN 10.83万磅
每台推力都超过十万磅 尾焰直冲无人船的表面
each firing over 100,000lbs of thrust towards the surface of the droneship.
随着火箭接近无人船 其尾焰会给无人船带来巨大的震动
As the rocket gets closer, the thrust from the engines starts to shake the droneship
震动大到会让无人船给卫星的上行链路失锁
with such a high frequency that the video feed antenna loses lock with the satellite,
从而造成视频断流
causing the video feed to cut out.
当火箭着陆停稳 震动消失后
Once the rocket has landed and the vibrations have dissipated,
视频画面就会恢复 大家突然就会看到辣么大一个火箭停在无人船的靶心
the video feed would usually reappear, showing a rocket standing tall in the middle of the droneship.
在我们之前的视频中曾提到用第二条船的解决办法
In our previous video about the droneship camera, many of you suggested having a secondary ship,
让第二条船离着陆船足够远 避免受到震动
far away from the droneship which wouldn't be affected by the vibrations.
虽然这个方案需要非常非常长的视频线连接两条船 但理论上是可行的
Despite the need for an extremely large video cable to connect the two ships, this option could work.
但现实中要考虑成本与回报
But it comes down to cost vs benefit.
想要实现这种事情 太空叉就得给自己家再添一条船
每次回收就要多花上百万美元 却只为了能看到流畅的着陆画面
This would add millions of dollars to the recovery cost, all for the sake of having a live video feed.
于是太空叉开始寻找一种更加精妙的视频直播解决方案
So, SpaceX started to search for a more elegant solution to fix their video feed.
巧了 他们家刚好还在搞一个全球低轨互联网通信系统 名字叫Starlink
Luckily, SpaceX also happened to be working on an internet communications system called Starlink.
部署完成后 Starlink可以为全球每一个偏僻的角落都能提供高速互联网服务
When fully operational, this massive constellation will provide high speed internet
to almost every part of the globe, including the most rural areas.
而正是这样的卫星通信技术帮助太空叉的无人船改善了数据回传的状况
But it's actually the satellite technology itself that proved to be very useful for SpaceX's droneship.
Starlink的锅用的是相控阵列
Starlink dishes have a phased array antenna,
用的时候它自己不用动就能把信号发送给卫星
which allows the signal to be directed towards a satellite without any moving parts.
它利用波的相长干涉和相消干涉 让电磁波指向特定的方向
It uses destructive and constructive interference to steer the radio wave in the right direction.
有了对信号指向更灵活的控制 与对震动更强的抵抗力后
With more control over the direction of the signal and stronger resistance to the intense vibrations,
这些Starlink的天线让信号的传输比之前传统的指向天线更加稳定
these Starlink dishes seem to provide a more stable connection
than the standard transmitters they were using before.
事实也的确如此 今年早些时候我们就已经在无人船上看到了Starlink天线
Sure enough, we started to see Starlink dishes appear on the droneships earlier this year.
表面上看视频信号的确稳定多了
Although this seems to have improved the overall video signal,
但这背后也没那么简单
it's not as simple as it may seem.
因为Starlink星座部署还处于早期阶段
Since the Starlink satellites are still in an early design phase,
还无法使用星间链路
they don't yet have the ability to communicate with each other.
所以目前 每个卫星都要和地球上的地面站进行通讯
For now, each satellite can only communicate with ground stations on Earth.
所以在无人船传回视频的例子中
So when it comes to sending a video signal from the droneship,
卫星必须处在能同时看到无人船和佛罗里达地面站的位置
a satellite needs to be in range of both the droneship and the ground station in Florida.
这些卫星目前大多数轨道高度是约550公里
The majority of these satellites currently orbit at an altitude of around 550km
每个能覆盖950公里范围的区域
and each one can cover an area of 950km.
所以多数离岸600公里左右的海上着陆
With most droneship landings taking place around 600km offshore,
一颗卫星应该足以接收信号并传回给地面站
a single satellite should be capable of receiving the signal and sending it down to the ground station.
但卫星自己在天上是高速移动的
However since each satellite moves across the sky very quickly,
所以无人船上的Starlink锅很可能要在前一个卫星跑出范围后
the Starlink dish on the droneship will most likely have to switch between multiple different satellites
切换到下一个卫星
as each one goes out of range.
就好像你的手机在不同信号基站之间切换一样
This should happen seamlessly just like your phone switching between data towers.
最终结果就是一次完美稳定的视频画面
The result is a perfectly stable video signal
从火箭进入大气开始 一直到稳稳停在无人船上
from the time the rocket enters the atmosphere, all the way through to it touching down on the droneship.
宏观来看 他们只是解决了一个很小的问题
In the grand scheme of things, this was a small problem to fix -
放到很多公司可能根本不会在乎这个
and one that most companies wouldn't have put any time or effort into.
但太空叉明白 让大家看到工程上这样了不起的时刻有多么重要
But SpaceX understands how important it is for people to witness these incredible moments of engineering.
六年前他们第一次让一级火箭着陆的时候
When they landed their first rocket 6 years ago,
人们很难理解这般庞然大物是如何在精准的控制下着陆的
it was hard to understand how something so large could land with so much control.
而如今这些火箭着陆的画面已成为家常便饭
The fact that landings like this have become so routine,
让世人知道太空叉如何彻底改变了航天工业
shows how much SpaceX has revolutionized the space industry.
而他们还有殖民火星的宏伟计划
With their ambitious plans to colonize Mars,
所以需要更多的人对未来的航天事业感兴趣
they need more and more people to be interested in the future of spaceflight.
即使是像这样一个不起眼的问题
Even a relatively non-important problem like this
也需要太空叉最聪明的人进行大量巧妙的工程设计
required a lot of clever engineering from SpaceX's brightest minds.
太空叉要想做到这些
With everything that SpaceX does,
就需要找到一群最聪明、最有雄心的、拥有适合技能的工人
they look for the smartest and most ambitious workers with the right skills for the job.
原视频工商时间 不翻了
那么有没有一款……
Skillshare is an online learning community with thousands of inspiring classes
designed to feed the creativity and curiosity of people like you.
With some of the best teachers at your fingertips,
you can learn about anything from photography to music production - all the way to business and entrepreneurship.
More and more people are now starting their own YouTube channels to share their passions with the world.
Whether you want to document the future of spaceflight or show off your unique skill,
check out this class called 'YouTube Success' by Marques Brownlee.
Whether you know a lot about the YouTube industry or are just starting out,
this class covers everything you need to know.
With years of experience, Marques takes you from the process of content creation all the way to strategies on growing your channel.
With thousands of classes available on Skillshare, pick the one that's right for you and start learning!
Skillshare has no ads and there are always new premium classes being launched.
The first 1000 people to sign up using the link below will get a 1 month free trial of skillshare premium.
非常感谢大家的观看 我们下期视频见
Thank you very much for watching and I'll see you in the next video.